What is radiation?
Why is it important?
Radiation treatment
can be thought of as high energy rays,
like powerful
x-rays that are directed at the tumors
to stop the cells
from growing and dividing.
This video series focuses
specifically on external beam radiation,
in which the radiation is delivered
from an energy source
outside the body through a beam of energy.
No radiation is implanted within the body,
but you may hear of another
type of radiation called brachytherapy,
which is internal.
That will not be discussed here.
Radiation works
because these X-ray beams cause breaks
in the DNA of the cancer cells,
which prevents them from surviving.
This is also how radiation targets
the cancer cells
while sparing your healthy cells.
Your healthy cells
have the cellular machinery
within them to repair these DNA breaks
so the healthy cells can survive
while the cancer cells, due
to their abnormal growth, do not have
the tools necessary to repair the DNA.